Designing cost functions is difficult and getting them
コスト関数を設計することは難しく
all to cooperate to produce reasonable vehicle behavior is hard.
また合理的な自動車の動作を生成するために 全部を連携させることは難しいです
Some of the difficulties associated with cost functions design
コスト関数の設計に関連したいくつかの難しい点は 古い問題を解決せずに
include solving new problems without unsolving old ones.
新しい問題を解決することも含まれます
When you're working on a self-driving car,
自動運転車で作業をしているとき
you may find that the vehicle is behaving reasonably
一部の特定の状況を除いて
well except for some particular situations.
自動車はとても合理的に動作していると思うかもしれません
Maybe it's not being aggressive enough about making left turns at traffic lights.
信号で左に曲がるには 積極的でなさすぎるのかもしれません
So, in an effort to solve this problem,
この問題を解決するために
you either add new cost functions,
新しいコスト関数を追加する
tweak existing ones, or modify the weights.
既にあるものを微調整する または重みを変更するのいずれかを行います
But every time you do,
でもそれを行うといつも
there's a chance that you will introduce
既にうまくいっているところで
some breaking change into something that already works.
別の問題が出てくる可能性があります
In practice, we solve this through regression testing,
実際に 予期したように動作している状況セットを
where we define some set of situations,
いくつか設定した回帰テストを使って
each of which has an expected behavior.
解決します
Then, whenever we make a change,
変更するといつでも
we simulate the vehicle in all of
今までのすべてのテストケースで自動車をシミュレートし
our test cases and make sure that it still behaves as expected.
予期したように動作するようにします
We won't say more about testing here,
ここでは テストについてはこれ以上話しませんが
but it is an important part of developing software in a safety-critical application.
セーフティクリティカルなアプリケーションでのソフトウェアの開発においては重要な部分です
The next difficulty is balancing costs of drastically different magnitudes.
次の難しい点は 極端に異なる高さのコストを均等にすることです
Because, yes, we want to get to our destination efficiently,
というのは もちろん目的地に効率的にたどり着きたいですが
but if we are in a situation where safety is an issue,
安全面で問題がある場合は
we want to solve that problem and not think about efficiency at all.
その問題を解決することを考え 効率的かどうかは全く考慮しません
One way to do that is to have weights which
これを行うには コスト関数が揚げている問題のタイプを
reflect the type of problem the cost function addresses.
反映する重みをもつことです
So we want to most heavily penalize
物理学的に
any behavior which simply isn't possible due to physics,
絶対可能ではない動作を極力不利にして
then we want to think about safety, legality, comfort.
安全性 適正 快適さについて考えようとします
And only once those are satisfied do we want to think about efficiency.
それらがクリアになってから 効率について考えます
But we also may want to adjust
でも 状況によりこれらの重みの関連する重要性を調整することを考えます
If a light turns red, for example,
たとえば 信号が赤になると
legality becomes a much more relevant concern
通常の高速道路の運転で考えるときよりも
than when we engage in normal highway driving.
適正についてもっと考えることになります
And this leads us to our last difficulty,
そして これが 個々のコスト関数について論理的に考えるという
reasoning about individual cost functions.
最後の難しい点につながっていきます
Ideally, each cost function will serve a very specific responsibility,
理想的には、それぞれのコスト関数は固有の役割を果たします
which is something we didn't do in our earlier example of a speed cost function.
これは速度コスト関数の最初のころの例ではしてなかったことです
We were trying to balance our desire to drive quickly,
早く運転するために 要望を均等化しようとしていました
which has to do with efficiency,
それは 法律を厳守した速度制限を超えないということを考えながら
with our desire to not exceed the speed limit, which is legality.
効率を意識して行う必要があります
In practice, we might want to define
実際 自動車速度に関連するコスト関数を
several cost functions associated with vehicle speed.
いくつか定義しようと考えるかもしれません
In which case we might have a binary cost function which just checks to see if we are
その場合 法定速度を超えてないかをチェックするだけの
breaking the speed limit and the continuous
バイナリコスト関数と
cost function which pulls us towards our target speed.
目標速度に向けて加速させる継続コスト関数があるかもしれません
By assigning each cost function to a very specific role,
安全性 適正 効率性などの非常に特有の役割を
like safety versus legality versus efficiency,
それぞれのコスト関数を割り当てることで
we can then standardize the output of all cost functions to be between -1 and 1.
すべてのコスト関数の出力を -1 ～ 1 に標準化できます
Additionally, it's helpful to parametrize whenever possible.
さらに いつでも可能な時にパラメーター化することに役立ちます
This allows us to use some parameter optimization technique like
これで 回帰テスト一式と併せた勾配降下法のような
gradient descent along with our set of
いくつかのパラメーター最適化テクニックを使用して
regression tests to programmatically tweak our cost functions.
プログラムでコスト関数を微調整できます
Finally, thinking in terms of vehicle state is helpful.
最終的に 自動車の状態の面においては役立ちます
The things we can indirectly control about
車両に関して間接的に制御できることは
our vehicle are its position, velocity, and acceleration.
その位置 速度 および加速度です
It can be helpful to keep these in mind when coming up with cost functions.
コスト関数について考えるとき これらを頭に置いておくと役立ちます
Let's walk through an example.
例を見てみましょう
Say we want to think about the following classes of cost functions.
コスト関数の次のクラスについて考えてみます
And to make it easier,
また簡単にするために
to keep everything straight,
すべてはっきりしておくために
let's think in terms of position, velocity, and acceleration.
位置 速度 加速度について考えてみましょう
The binary "Are we exceeding the speed?"
バイナリ 「速度を超えていますか? 」
cost function would go here,
コスト関数がここにきて
then the cost function that wanted to keep us close to the speed limit would go here.
速度制限内に収まるようにしておくためのコスト関数はここにきます
And now, instead of being that weird discontinuous graph we made earlier,
また 前に作成したへんなうまくつながってないグラフではなく
this could just be some parabola like this.
このような放物線になります
And even though the cost of this is low even for speeds that exceed the speed limit,
速度制限を超える速度のこのコストが低くても
that's OK because we have our binary cost function which would prevent that behavior.
そのような動作を予防するバイナリコスト関数があるので それは大丈夫です
Continuing to think about speed,
速度について引き続き考えていきます
we also might want to try to drive at
安全面のことを考えて 交通量の平均速度が制限速度より遅い
a speed that's close to the average speed of traffic,
または速い場合でも その平均速度で走行したいと
for safety reasons, even if that speed is above or below the speed limit.
考えることもあると思います
And that would go here.
それはここで行います
In the position column,
位置カラムで
we'd have an obvious feasibility concern which is collision avoidance.
絶対に起こりうる心配があります それは衝突の回避です
We can't drive somewhere if there is already a car there.
既に車があるところでは 走行できません
Then, for safety reasons,
安全面の理由から
we would want the buffer distance,
バッファ距離を確保したいです
which tries to keep us far from other vehicles,
それによりほかの自動車と十分な距離を保とうとします
and the cost function which checks to make sure we are driving on
また必ず車線の真ん中に近い道路で
the road near the center of our lane and in a lane that's close to our goal lane.
ゴールの車線に近い車線を走行しているかどうかをチェックするするコスト関数が必要です
For acceleration, we'd first want to
加速については
make sure we only consider behaviors that the car can execute,
まず車が実行できる動作のみを考慮し
and then we'd want to avoid having any rapid changes in
そのうえで加速が急変化するのを
acceleration because those are perceived as uncomfortable.
避けようとします
This is also known as jerk which you'll learn more about in the next lesson.
これについては 次のレッスン詳しく学習する jerk とし知られています
Consider a merge onto a highway, for example.
たとえば高速道路での合流を考えてみましょう
This is a potentially dangerous situation where we really
これはできるだけ早く交通速度に上げる必要がある、
want to get up to traffic speed as quickly as possible.
潜在的に危険な状況です
So this cost function may become more relevant than it normally is.
よって そのため、このコスト関数は通常以上により重要な要素になる可能性があります
But we also want to make sure that we yield if there isn't really a gap,
しかし 必ず十分な車間距離がない場合は速度を落とすようにします
so we want to make sure this cost function and this one are weighted sufficiently high.
そのため このコスト関数とこれが十分に高くなっているか測定します
And we can compare these merge priorities to a different situation.
また これらの合流の優先度を、異なる状況と比較することができます
For example, a car approaching a green light that suddenly turns yellow.
たとえば 車が青信号に近づいてるときに 突然黄色に変わったとします
In this situation, we'd probably want to boost the weights associated with
この状況では 合法に関する重みを上げて
legality and would probably need to add
交通規則に従うために まったく新しいコスト関数を
a whole new cost function for obeying traffic rules.
追加する必要があると思います
Now that doesn't fall neatly into the position,
それはうまくその位置
velocity, or acceleration classes,
速度 または加速クラスに収まりません
so I'll just put it over here.
そのため ここにおいておきます
If this is all starting to feel like it's getting pretty complex, well, you're right.
これが複雑だと感じさせるようであれば それは正しいです
It's pretty hard to avoid this exploding complexity when using finite state machines.
finite state machines を使用している場合は この展開される複雑さを回避することはとても難しいです
Partially that's because of the finite state machine itself,
finite state machine それ自身の一部であるからです
but we're also trying to solve a very hard problem and
でも 非常に難しい問題を解決しようとしています
some complexity is unavoidable no matter what solution approach you take.
また どのソリューションを使ったとしても 一部の複雑さは回避できません